Hello, welcome back to our statistical programming language course. Today, we are going to continue where we stopped last time. So, last time, we installed R and RStudio,
and then in the video, you are able to see that particular window.
You might be wondering why once you installed RStudio and R on your computers,
your RStudio looked slightly different. And this is because I customised
how my R studio looks like. And how do we do it? Well, first, we need to go to Tools,
then click on Global Options. And then go to Appearance.
Now, if we go to the Editor theme and scroll down,
you will see that I selected "Tomorrow Night Bright" theme.
Why did I do it? Well, because otherwise, it would be slightly difficult for you
to see lightly colored captions. Most likely, once you downloaded
RStudio, the default theme was selected for you, and the default theme
is this text-made theme. And as you can see, the default theme is very light colored, so it would be
quite difficult to see the captions there. So let me go back to my theme. Another difference is
the pane layout. What is the pane? Pane is this tiny window here.
And most likely, once you downloaded RStudio, the pane layout was the default one, and the default one was with
having a console. On the left
at the bottom. So, let us go back to that default layout,
and then let us click "Apply".
Let me just minimize that pane, because we are going to come back to it.
Alright, so now let us do some coding. We can go straight to the console, and maybe we could write, for example,
print("Hello World")
Alright. And then we have enter. Alright, you can see that we printed our first line of code in RStudio,
which is "Hello World". We can also define some covariates, for example
A could be 4 and B could be a vector from 1 to 4.
So, what are we seeing right now? On the left-hand side, we are seeing that I'm really coding something.
And then, on the right-hand side, I can see in that
pane on the right-hand side that in the environment, these values, the
one variable, A, and this vector are defined.
What can we also see on the right-hand side? We could click on that history tab
and we could see that history records everything what we put
inside the console. So this is sort of a record
of what we have written during a particular session. Okay, but working with a
console is not a traditional way of interacting. Once we would like to write big chunks of codes,
we would like to then change them in the future. So, how do we do it? Usually, we need some
file, where we store the code. And here in R, we use scripts.
So, precisely, now we have that forth
pane opened, and then here, once again, I can write certain
lines of codes. For example, let me redefine that vector B, so B
is from 1 to 4, and then to execute that line, either I click CTRL
enter, or command enter. Depends if you are on Windows machine or Mac.
What has happened here? Okay, so we can see that B was redefined, I cannot see the second B, it's just the same B, but redefined.
We can see that we executed that line of code, because I have B
for the second time in the console, and then if we go to the history, you can see
that here, we have B executed for the first time, and B executed for the second time.
Okay, now, um, what about writing something else? Let us write now, in our script, another line of code, for example, something like that.
So I will tell you shortly what that is. I would like to now define
a vector, which is
one hundred elements long. And it spans from 0 to 5.
How can I do it? Well, instead of thinking about all elements of the vector, I can use that function seq(),
and then I just define the starting value, I define the
last value, and I define the length of that particular vector.
But how can I check? What does this particular function do? Well, we could basically write,
?seq and then execute.
Okay, what's going on now? Now, we could see that
in the fourth pane, we have a description
of this function. So we can see that this is a function which generates sequences, and then we could see
how this function
was defined. So, basically, we can select the first element and the last element,
and we could select the length of that particular vector. Alright, this is the first function you have seen, this seq function, but let us now apply
for each element of this function, another function:
Sin function. So, what does it do? Basically, if I write at this particular line,
I ask R to apply sine function to each and every single element of a vector C.
How do I check? If it worked, well, of course we could see that
In the environment, that particular, the second vector, is defined.
But maybe we could actually plot these two elements
and see if that sine function appears. And indeed, it appears. So we can see, that on the x-axis, we have that vector C,
we have vector D on the y-axis, and you can see that the default option for the plot,
the basic plot in R is this plot composed of these dots.
We could, of course, change a different type
of the plot. And now, we changed the
type to just a solid line. In the right bottom pane,
we could have seen already the help
tab, we could have seen also the plots tab. But now I can also go back and see
the first plot we generated. Here, we have the first plot. So we can see that it's
very user-friendly to use RStudio. Now, if we
would like to go further and see what is in other tabs,
let us click on files tab. So what can we see here? Here we can just see directories in our home directory.
And of course, it would vary for your machine.
Then, we could also see that tab with
packages. Okay, so what is a package? Package is a super useful thing, because basically, it's a bundle
of different functions in R. So, you can see here different names of packages, and these names
were already pre-installed on your machine. So now, for example, if I would like to
access that bundle, that package, what do I do? I just check this box, and you can see immediately that on my
bottom left, a code was actually executed. And then this bundle
is just brought to me, and I can now access the function from that package.
Another thing we could do is install packages. So, for example,
people, once derived the packages, the functions, and they bundle them into the packages they would like to share them with the world,
and they saw them on that, CRAN repository. And then, if I know the name of a package, I can just
try to write the first letter, and then xgboost, it's a very popular package. Let's try to install it.
Okay, so we click on xgboost. And then we install it. So we can see that once again, the installation was
executed by RStudio.
We could see that, indeed, the downloaded binary packages are stored in that particular
directory, in that particular folder. Okay, so another thing here is
viewer tab. A viewer tab is a sort of a tiny browser.
And the presentation tab, the presentation tab is useful once we make presentations
using RMarkdown. And we are going to come back to RMarkdown later.
Alright, so I would say this is the basic intro into different panes.
There is one last thing, which is extremely important: How to write comments in R. So basically,
it's very important to write comments inside your code.
Not only for others, to help them understand, but mainly for yourself.
Trust me, in a few months' time, you won't remember many things from your code.
And how do we do it? Well, we just write this hashtag.
And then, for example, you can write "This is my first comment in RStudio."
Alright, and this is my second comment "This is the second comment."
All right. And once we are ready to then share
our code, or once we are just ready with our work for today, of course,
we need to save the script. How do we do it?
We go to file, and then we save it as something.
Let me just write code1, and I save it.
And finally, let me just go back to Tools once again.
Because, I told you that inside the tools, you can change the appearance of the entire
Rstudio, but you could also change the appearance of how your
script looks like. So, if we go to Tools, and we go to Global Options,
and we go to Code, you can see that there are many different options. One of them,
kind of important one for readability of your code, is this margin. So basically here, I can change where the margin is. The margin is this
lightly colored grey line. Why is it important? Because it's easier to read code that isn't written in white. So the lines of codes.
shouldn’t be written in colours that are too light. Okay that's it for now.
Thank you, and yeah, we are going to see each other.